Guide to the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA.012
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection
1990-1991
AIA.012
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
Thirty-four 34 origional audio tapes and access CD-Rom copies comprise the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History The interviees include civil rights lawyer and politician Paul O'Dwyer (29 tapes), Irish Northern Aid founder Michael Flannery (4 tapes), and Kings County District Attorney Charles J. Hynes (1 tape). These interviews were produced as a part of an oral history project with the New York Irish History Roundtable to record the lives and experiences of those of Irish ancestry. Transcripts of the O'Dwyer interviews are included with the Cds.
Muller, Jane Conlon.
Provenance
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Paul O’Dwyer
Born in Lismirrane, Parish of Bohola, County Mayo, Ireland, O'Dwyer was a politician and lawyer noted for his dedication to civil rights. Arriving in the U.S. in 1925, O'Dwyer enrolled in St. John's Law School the following year and graduated in 1931. In 1932, he joined the law firm O'Dwyer and Bernstein. He began his career defending pickets against labor-organizing injunctions, opposing the deportation of foreign-born agitators, and defending the rights of unionists to organize. He was a member of the National Lawyers Guild and served as president of the New York chapter in 1947.
O'Dwyer gained success in the courtroom, where he continuously fought for the underdog. He participated in almost every civil-rights struggle in America during the second half of the twentieth century. He worked at registration drives for African Americans in Mississippi during the 1960s, defended Communists and Communist sympathizers during the McCarthy era, vigorously protested the Vietnam War, and battled for the foundation of the state of Israel.
O'Dwyer participated in politics both by working behind the scenes on other candidates' campaigns and by running his own campaigns. He assisted in John F. Kennedy's 1962 presidential campaign and David Dinkins' 1998 mayoral campaign. O'Dwyer's own campaigns were less successful; out of a dozen electoral efforts, he lost all but two: the 1963 race for councilman-at-large in Manhattan and the 1973 race for City Council President.
O'Dwyer managed to maintain his identity as an Irish nationalist and fully embrace his role as an Irish American. The quest for a united Ireland remained close to his heart and during his frequent visits back to Ireland, he met with all sides of the conflict, including the Irish Republican Army, the Ulster Defense Association, and the Irish government. He introduced the McBride principles to the United States government, which prevent U.S. government agencies from investing in Northern Ireland companies that discriminate against their employees. He transformed his childhood home into the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home for disabled children and adults and established the O'Dwyer Forestry Foundation, both to fund the Cheshire home in the future, and also in an effort to reforest part of Ireland.
In addition to his civil rights work in the U.S., O'Dwyer was involved in many Irish-American organizations, including the United Irish Counties Association, the Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association, the New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee, and the Gaelic Athletic Association. His love for New York City and its history led him to assist in the creation of the Department of Records and Information Services (D.O.R.I.S.) to oversee the Municipal Archives and to become the Manhattan Borough Historian in 1986. He was the founder in 1950 of the Irish Institute of New York, Inc., a philanthropic group.
In 1990 O'Dwyer was appointed the New York City Commissioner to the United Nations and Consular Corps. In this capacity he was instrumental in having the Brehon Law Society admitted to the UN as a non-governmental organization.
O'Dwyer, time and again, demonstrated his commitment to protect the rights of people, regardless of their race, religion, or gender and did so with remarkable grace and sense of purpose. After a series of small strokes, O'Dwyer retired to his home in Goshen, New York where he died on June 12, 1998.
Michael Flannery
Michael Flannery, a militant Irish nationalist, was born in Knockshegowna, a small village in the North of County Tipperary, Ireland. He spent his early childhood working on his parents' farm and attending school, but by 1916, the year of the Easter Uprising, Flannery left school to join the Irish Volunteers, a nationalist organization that would later become the Irish Republican Army (IRA). During his active duty with the IRA during both the War for Independence (1919-1921) and the Civil War (1922-1923), Flannery patrolled the Irish countryside, ambushing British soldiers. The British eventually captured him and sent him to prison for two years. In 1927, Flannery emigrated to the United States, married, settled in Jackson Heights, Queens, NY and found a job with Metropolitan Life Insurance Company.
A devout Catholic, Flannery attended Mass every morning at his local church and neither smoked nor drank. His quiet, undemonstrative character and devotion to the Irish nationalist cause brought him respect and admiration in the Irish-American community. Flannery's participation in a multitude of organizations including the Clan na Gael, American Congress for Irish Freedom, Gaelic Athletic Association, and Irish Action Committee, earned him the following remark from his lawyer, Frank Durkan: "If there was going to be a meeting of six people in the north Bronx in the middle of a snowstorm, the only man you knew would be there was Michael Flannery."
As the civil rights movement in Northern Ireland gained momentum in 1969, tensions increased between Catholics and Protestants and the IRA again rose to the forefront of the struggle. Flannery helped to found the Irish Northern Aid Committee (Noraid) in 1970 to raise funds in the United States to support the families of IRA soldiers who were killed or imprisoned in the North. While the British, Irish, and United States governments believed Noraid to be a front for the IRA, Flannery insisted that, while he supported the IRA's tactics, the money raised by Noraid did not go to buy arms.
In 1981, Flannery and four other men were charged with gunrunning for the IRA ( U.S. vs. Harrison, Falvey, Mullen, Gormley and Flannery). The FBI accused Flannery of handling the money in the transaction. The counsel defending Flannery and the other men took an aggressive strategy during the trial by putting forth the idea that the defendants believed that they were working for the CIA. Since the CIA has a license to export weapons, they did not believe they were breaking any laws. This tactic put the burden on the prosecution to prove that the CIA was not involved and the jury found all five men innocent. Flannery was the only one of the defendants to testify, and he used that opportunity to deliver an impassioned speech about Irish history and British oppression.
Capitalizing on the publicity from the trial, Irish republicans campaigned to elect Flannery as the Grand Marshal of the New York St. Patrick's Day Parade in 1983. Given Flannery's open support of the IRA and the recent trial, his nomination did not come without a swarm of controversy. But despite opposition by prominent politicians, community leaders, the Catholic Church and the Irish government, the parade drew a record crowd.
In 1989, Noraid altered its focus to acknowledge the Dublin government and incorporate political measures in resolving the conflict. Flannery and other veterans of his generation believed that a focus on political activities would detract from the fundraising aspects of Noraid and would ultimately compromise the primary function of the organization. After failing to resolve the differences between his personal beliefs and the new direction the organization was taking, Flannery resigned from Noraid in 1986. He joined the Friends of Irish Freedom in 1989, which had the exclusive purpose of raising money for families of IRA prisoners. He continued his support for FOIF and the militant republican cause until his death in 1994.
Charles J. Hynes
Charles J. Hynes was born in Brooklyn in 1935. As a second-generation Irish American, Hynes first remembers developing his Irish identity from the stories that his grandfather would tell him about emigrating to Boston and the discrimination against the Irish that he witnessed. Although a member of the Ancient Order of Hibernians since the early 1970s, Hynes only became publicly active in Irish-American activities during the 1981 hunger strikes. His outrage at how the British government was treating the hunger strikers led him to join in the protests at the British Embassy and eventually to co-found Irish Solidarity Day.
Hynes graduated from St. John's University Law School in 1961. He began his public service career as an associate attorney with the Brooklyn Legal Aid society. He later became a special state prosecutor in 1985, where he remained until he was elected as the Brooklyn District Attorney in 1989. Hynes has run two unsuccessful primary campaigns for other elected positions: the 1994 race for state attorney general and the 1998 race for governor of New York. He has also taught as an adjunct professor at St. John's Law School, Brooklyn Law School, and Fordham Law School.
All the interviews were conducted in 1990 and 1991 by Jane Conlon Muller, an attorney and member of the Roundtable. She first interviewed O'Dwyer, who suggested that she also interview Flannery. At this time, Muller worked in the Kings County DA's office, which was the impetus for interviewing Hynes. Jane Conlon Muller (b. 3/16/1942) is the granddaughter of Irish immigrants from counties Donegal, Leitrim and Clare. She holds a bachelors degree from Queens College and a Juris Doctorate from CUNY Law School. After leaving the Kings County DA's office, she opened her own law practice, which specializes in construction law, elder law, wills, trusts and estates as well as real estate.
Sources:
Glazier, Michael, ed. The Encyclopedia of the Irish in America. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1999.
O'Dwyer, Paul. Counsel for the Defense:the Autobiography of Paul O'Dwyer. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1979.
Rohan, Brian. "Paul O'Dwyer, 90, Remembered as a Hero." Irish Voice. 7 July 1998, 3.
Hampson, Rick. "The Old Man and the Gun." New York Beacon. 31 March 1995, 35.
Holland, Jack. The American Connection: U.S. Guns, Money, and Influence in Northern Ireland. Boulder, CO: Roberts Rinehart Publishers, 1999.
Mullins, Elmer. "Boylan Blazes: Veteran Republican Flannery Dies at 92." Irish America. 21 November 1994, 15.
Rohan, Brian. "He Did Not Go Gently: An IRA Burial in Queens for Mike Flannery." Irish Voice. 11 October 1994, 8.
Wilson, Andrew J. Irish America and the Ulster Conflict, 1968-1995. Washington, DC: The Catholic University of America Press, 1995.
Barbanel, Josh. "Hynes to Enter Race for Brooklyn District Attorney." New York Times. #1 June 1989. B:2
Perez-Pena, Richard. "The Democratic Candidates for Governor at a Glance." New York Times. 13 September 1998, 56.
Scope and Content Note
This finding aid includes a log with summaries of the interview content as well as Muller's questions compiled at ten-minute intervals. The collection consists of access copies on CD-Rom (Box 1) and original cassettes (Box 2). The originals are for preservation only and not to be used. Three folders included with the collection contain an overivew of the collection and interviews and transcripts for Paul O'Dwyer's interview.
Arrangement
The cassettes are numbered 1-34. The CDs are also numbered and arranged into three series by interviewee:
I. Paul O’Dwyer (1907-1998)
II. Michael Flannery (1902-1994)
III. Charles J. Hynes (1935 - )
Related Material
Paul O’Dwyer’s personal and official papers are housed at St. John’s University, Jamaica, New York and at the Municipal Archives, 31 Chambers Street, New York City. An oral history conducted with him in 1962 is preserved in Box 20 at Columbia University’s Oral History Research Office, Room 801 Butler Library, New York City.
American Congress for Irish Freedom.; Clan-na-Gael.; Flannery, Michael, 1902-1994.; Gaelic Athletic Association.; Hynes, Charles J., 1935-; Irish Action Committee.; Irish Republican Army.; Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association.; New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee.; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-; United Irish Counties Association.; CD-ROMs.; Ireland |x Politics and government |y 20th century.; Irish Americans |x Societies, etc.; Lawyers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Revolutionaries |z Ireland.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest movements.
- Guide to Collection and transcripts for Paul O'Dwyer interviews, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
- Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998) (partial transcript included in two folders), 1990-1991
  Scope and Contents note
  The 22 interviews with O'Dwyer were conducted between February 1990 and May 1991 in his office at the United Nations building in Manhattan. He viewed these oral histories as a sort of continuation of his autobiography, Counsel for the Defense, which was published in 1979. Although he discusses some of the issues also touched on in his book, such as educating African-Americans about voting in Mississippi during the 1960s, presiding over the New York City Council, and his participation in the 1968 Democratic National Convention, O'Dwyer also discusses his experiences both in Ireland and in America since writing the book.
  The interviews contain much information relevant to Irish-American studies, such as insights into the history of Irish immigration and experiences in America especially in New York, Irish-American athletics, radio shows, and newspapers, and the New York St. Patrick's Day parade. O'Dwyer recounts his experiences as a politician in the U.S., including running for various offices, the development and success of the McBride principles, his relationship to the Jewish community in New York, his relationship with Senator Daniel Moynihan, and his work with the United Nations. He also discusses his experiences as a lawyer, including his involvement with professional organizations, such as the National Lawyers Guild and the Brehon Law Society and specific cases he worked on, such as the Fort Worth Five and Joe Doherty.
  O'Dwyer also discusses Ireland - the history of the discontent between Catholics and Protestants in the North, the civil rights movement, the 1981 hunger strikes, Irish travelers, and the development of the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home and O'Dwyer Forestry Foundation.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Paul O'Dwyer introduced. O'Dwyer's hopes to create an informal hearing to gather information about the reasons (or excuses) the United States used to invade Panama in 1989. Discussion about how Americans allow the government to get away with things by remaining silent on important issues as seen with President Reagan in Grenada and President Bush in Panama. [10:00 - 20:00] Participation in Mayor Dinkins' election. Involvement in other civil rights oriented elections, including electing an African American man to be the mayor of Sunflower, Mississippi. Civil rights cases in the South, including a case in Jackson, Mississippi where he represented a black man who lost his job and whose house was firebombed because he tried to register to vote. Judge's official opinion that African Americans are less intelligent than whites because their heads are smaller.Dangers of working in the South during the civil rights movement and the precautions he took, such as never riding in a car with an African American person.Work with the Freedom Democratic party on the campaign of Victoria Gray, an African American candidate for Congress. [20:00 - end] Work with Eleanor Owens Jackson, a professor of law at Georgetown University Law School. Jackson was in charge of COPAL(?), an amalgam of civil rights organizations including the National Lawyers Guild, of which O'Dwyer was a member. O'Dwyer's job was to go to African-American churches and educate them about voting. He tells of his experiences on that job, such as teaching young African Americans how to stay within the regulations for voting.Case of Lois Chaffee, a white teacher at Tougaloo College, who was arrested for disorderly conduct after police found her with African Americans after a protest march through Jackson, MI. (Cd 1, Track 1)
    General note
    [05:48] How far along have you gotten with forming this committee?
    [06:33] Do you have any idea at all why you think there was no opposition that you mentioned before?
    [08:15] Have you anyone on your committee that's been in Panama recently?
    [08:35] So you have a fact gathering committee in effect?
    [10:52] What state was that?
    [14:18] May I ask you what year this was?
    [17:25] Was this before or after that incident? When you were down there and you tried this case?
    [17:44] You took certain precautions that you've mentioned - what was your state of mind at that time when you were down there?
    [19:11] What office was she running for?
    [20:28] You constantly refer to 'we,' so you obviously weren't there by yourself. Could you tell us who else was a part of your group?
    [22:14] She graduated from where?
    [23:35] Was it just that they [African Americans] were inexperienced in voting or were they also afraid?
    [24:32] Am I to understand then that you went down at different times during the sixties and for certain lengths of times? 2 weeks? 3 weeks? Longer?
    [25:52] This was a somewhat organized movement then that you were a part of?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Chaffey case and difficulty finding a Mississippi lawyer. O'Dwyer brought an action against the mayor and governor and made them testify in this case to show how corrupt the establishment was and how it was depriving people of their rights.Another case concerning letting an African American woman use the public library where the courts ruled that she was allowed to use it, but no other African Americans could. [10:00 - 20:00] Discusses role of Catholic church in civil rights movement in Mississippi. Conversation with liberal local parish priest and his perspective on the civil rights movement. More on priests in Mississippi and their activities. [20:00 - end ] More on Mrs. King situation and civil rights in Mississippi. Explanation of freedom riders, more about what he was working on while staying with Mrs. King. For the election of the mayor and five councilmen, there were too many African American candidates for the number of positions available, so O'Dwyer had to convince two candidates to drop out so that the African American vote would not be split. One did rather easily, but a local minister was much more difficult to convince.First elected African American mayor in Sunflower (did not happen during that election). (Cd 1, Track 2)
    [08:48] We're just establishing here that Mr. O'Dwyer did not belong to a specific organization at that time. It's just a matter of record.
    [12:04] Was this priest of a local parish? That was his function? He was a local parish priest?
    [12:26] And they worked alone - these parish priests?
    [13:01] Am I correct in assuming when you say that out of the 125 priests in Mississippi 75 of them were from Ireland? Do you know the reason why?
    [13:34] So they actually then imported the priests from Ireland?
    [13:57] And were these priests, these Irish priests, were they volunteers to this community?
    Questions RE: Trip to Sunflower, MS with the purpose of convincing African Americans that voting works. Stayed in the home of Mrs. King, an African American woman whose house was firebombed because she accommodated freedom riders. His stay with her and more on her situation.
    [18:23] By what means did you get these accommodations? What network was working for you then?
    [19:48] This is in the north of Mississippi now? Where you were staying with her?
    [23:01] Did you sleep well that night?
    [27:57] What type of trouble? Specifically?
    [29:32] Did you meet with a lot of opposition in those days?
    [29:41] I mean something outright - that you were told to go home, stay out of our state, anything in that…?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] Case in Alligator, MS where O'Dwyer advised a group of young African Americans how to conduct themselves in court when they were being charged with ?? protest? Negotiations with Butler, the man in charge. [10:00 - 20:00] More on civil rights in the South. Practicalities of practicing law away from own office. [20:00 - end] More on Hazard case. Four of the eight defendants were illiterate. Attempt to transfer case to Lexington. One of the miners became a preacher during trial. Discussion of Baptist preachers. Discusses Simpson as his campaign manager for 1968 campaign to become a U.S. Senator. (Cd 2, Track 1)
    [2:40] But these young people must have been very frightened. They didn't? I was going to ask how you allayed their fears, but…?
    [3:04] It seemed to be maybe more of an adventure to them?
    [10:21] When you were representing, defending people, down in Mississippi, who did your paperwork?
    [10:41] Mostly done in New York then?
    [10:57] But what if you had to make various changes and stuff?
    [11:12] Nobody would actually say, "Come in - use my office" while you were there. There was no such thing as that?
    Questions RE: O'Dwyer's experiences as a child in Ireland during the Black and Tan/War of Independence.
    [11:47] Where were your training grounds to do this kind of work and where did your desire come from within you?
    [12:42] How old were you at that time?
    Questions RE: Case of eight unemployed white miners charged with blowing up the entrance to a mine in Hazard, Kentucky. Work with Dan Jack Coombs, the only lawyer in Kentucky who would take the case. Attitude of local judge.
    [24:45] Do you know what denomination the preacher was?
    [26:20] These young boys - their illiteracy was perpetuated over time then. You have mentioned before that they were the result of settlers that had settled a long time ago. Is that correct?
    [26:36] And so they continued with this illiterate form throughout the age - even as recently as the seventies?
    [27:02] Do you know what prevented them from getting an education? Were there just not enough schools in that area?
    [27:29] Just following the Bible and listening to the local preacher would be enough?
    [28:14] He was your campaign manager when you were running for which office?
    [28:50] Did you feel that these businesses - your clients - that they were, the illiterate ones particularly, were they content with their lives other than this situation that came about? Did they seem like they were happy people?